<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Learn to code</title><description>Based on a true story</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.6</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 21:57:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Day 8 - Fantastic day!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today started with a research that you can see in my previous post, and somehow it took sooooo much time, that we were not able to start Battle Ships before lunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During lunchtime yesterday and today we had Lunch talks. One more great thing in the Makers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday as a&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/untitled/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f64a8df9-5174-4de5-826f-11d1ef1d762e</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 21:54:36 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today started with a research that you can see in my previous post, and somehow it took sooooo much time, that we were not able to start Battle Ships before lunch. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During lunchtime yesterday and today we had Lunch talks. One more great thing in the Makers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday as a guest we had a Director of &lt;a href="http://www.createeducation.co.uk/"&gt;CREATE Education Project&lt;/a&gt;. He told us a lot of pretty amazing stuff about 3D printing and how &lt;a href="https://ultimaker.com/"&gt;Ultimaker 3D Printers&lt;/a&gt; can be used for education. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today the founder of &lt;a href="https://www.lexoo.co.uk/"&gt;Lexoo&lt;/a&gt;, who also have a huge experience in development, gave us couple of advises on how to become a good developer (write no code!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the talk and meditation we came back to our main project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am so proud of myself today, because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I managed to go slow, and go through each detail in MVP,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I managed to explain to my partner some very important things about testing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We had a dramatic breakthrough in Battle Ships!!! &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a happy day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way home was thinking about my progress...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/m6TL3ak.jpg" alt="Imgur"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then saw this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/bbI4aht.jpg" alt="Imgur"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it just me, or is there a clear connection here? &lt;br&gt;
I wonder what my result will be!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Dependency inversion</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today we received a task to research the Dependency Inversion principle (one of the SOLID principles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependency appears between two classes when one class has to use instances of the other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Dependency Injection principle can help you to avoid many complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dependency Inversion Principle has two parts:&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/solid/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">0f5176f7-da03-498e-a462-d8cff08291d0</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2015 11:14:51 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today we received a task to research the Dependency Inversion principle (one of the SOLID principles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dependency appears between two classes when one class has to use instances of the other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Dependency Injection principle can help you to avoid many complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dependency Inversion Principle has two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High-level modules should not depend on low-level modules. Both should depend on abstractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abstractions should not depend upon details. Details should depend upon abstractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit unclear, right? Much easier to explain it with an example. &lt;br&gt;
Here is a simple code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Airport

  def traffic_control
    rain = Rain.new
    puts "Bad weather" if rain.heavy?
  end

end

class Rain

  def heavy?
    rand &amp;lt; 0.7
  end

end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the code above Rain is instantiated directly inside #traffic_control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if we need to check if it snows, not rains? And we have this new Snow class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Snow

  def heavy?
    rand &amp;lt; 0.2
  end

end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the initial example we have to change the code inside the method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But below is an example of better practice, following this principle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;class Airport

  def traffic_control (condition = Rain.new)
    puts "Bad weather" if condition.heavy?
  end

end

class Rain

  def heavy?
    rand &amp;lt; 0.7
  end

end

class Snow

  def heavy?
    rand &amp;lt; 0.2
  end

end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now without changing the code, we can check either rain or snow conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;airport = Airport.new  
airport.traffic_control  
airport.traffic_control(Snow.new)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also injection could be done through the initialize method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it works the same way with modules!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Tim!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 7  - Love Mondays!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;New week - new project. &lt;br&gt;
This week we are supposed to continue improving our skills in OOP (last week's task and weekend challenge were also about using OOP). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OOP is object oriented programming. As it comes from the title, object is the main thing here. Same as in real life.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-7/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8bcc0d4c-513a-437f-9bee-b7ce782edb37</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Sep 2015 21:54:38 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;New week - new project. &lt;br&gt;
This week we are supposed to continue improving our skills in OOP (last week's task and weekend challenge were also about using OOP). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OOP is object oriented programming. As it comes from the title, object is the main thing here. Same as in real life. And as in real life objects can communicate with each other. &lt;br&gt;
To make an object first you need to make a class (it is like a blueprint, from which you can create objects). You can write a class, like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-ruby"&gt;class Dog

  attr_reader :name  

  def initialize (name)
    @name = name
  end

  def bark
    "Woof!"
  end

end  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you can make a real object from this class!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;my_dog = Dog.new('Shokky!')  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And use this object to do stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;puts my_dog.name  
puts my_dog.bark
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Shokky!  
Woof!  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So using this simple technic this week we are supposed to make Battle Ships game! And this time the instructions are minimal. We are working on our own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a great field for creativity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What classes should there be? how they should communicate with each other? who knows more - a ship or a board? do we need a board at all? are there any missiles involved? what are the rules? should we play this game first for an hour or so for the inspiration?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh! And also today was David's birthday! Happy birthday David! &lt;br&gt;
Harry arranged a cake and we sang a birthday song! That was great! Best moment of the day.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 5-6 First weekend challenge</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I can not believe it is already Sunday and it is 11 pm!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just sat on a sofa with my computer 5 minutes ago and it was only Saturday, 9 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's all I want to say about our first weekend challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kidding. It was not so bad. It&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-5-6-first-weekend-challenge/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">f8985ec9-c679-4ea3-80a8-137f3161d698</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 21:39:01 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I can not believe it is already Sunday and it is 11 pm!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just sat on a sofa with my computer 5 minutes ago and it was only Saturday, 9 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's all I want to say about our first weekend challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kidding. It was not so bad. It covered everything we had done during the week. And it was good to go through all materials one more time. I hate tests and I love tests. They are awful. But they help a lot. If you have 20 tests, and then do a little change in your program and suddenly all 20 do not pass, it is a nice little hint that something might be wrong with what you are doing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all end up well. And &lt;a href="https://travis-ci.org/"&gt;Travis&lt;/a&gt; is my new best friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Z-z-z-Z-Z-z-z...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 4 - Friday!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you love what you do  - Fridays are always great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an excellent pair, he was so calm and nice, and SO attentive to details. I liked his way of learning very much, and from now on my motto is 'go slow!' It is important now&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-4-friday/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">bb6526f6-173b-4312-9265-c5ec7704aa5e</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 18:24:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Even if you love what you do  - Fridays are always great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an excellent pair, he was so calm and nice, and SO attentive to details. I liked his way of learning very much, and from now on my motto is 'go slow!' It is important now to understand every little detail, it will help a lot later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Fridays we have a group lunch. Everybody come to a room with their lunches and discuss stuff with each other, nothing formal, no agenda, just one more opportunity to have a chat with someone from your cohort, or with a senior or a coach. I talked with several people and it is so interesting that we all share very similar story about our old life: good work, enough money, but no energy, awful mornings when you have to go to work (especially Monday of course), and the worst part of the week is Sunday evening... And then (dream)Makers appeared in our lives! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to try to do this blog more technical starting from the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it is Friday evening, and there is a free beer on the kitchen at the Makers! &lt;br&gt;
First week at Makers passed as 1 day. &lt;br&gt;
And it was a great day! &lt;br&gt;
Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 3 - Curiouser and curiouser</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Another intense and productive day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our coach is fantastic! WHAT A SPEED! I need the whole day to assimilate information I receive in 15-20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming is good, had another great pair today, very calm and friendly. Together we have finished Post Challenge 3. The code is messy but&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-3-curiouser-and-curiouser/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">32435b9e-0dc4-4073-bcdf-b7e533be8feb</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 21:47:53 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Another intense and productive day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our coach is fantastic! WHAT A SPEED! I need the whole day to assimilate information I receive in 15-20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming is good, had another great pair today, very calm and friendly. Together we have finished Post Challenge 3. The code is messy but all tests pass! Refactoring stage is badly required (see the previous post for details).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really struggling in writing tests, but getting better in it I hope... (a voice in my head keeps repeating TRUST US TRUST US TRUST US)...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tube started to read Practical object-oriented design in Ruby by Sandi Metz.  So far seems like an excellent book.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Red Green Refactor</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today we've been given a task of researching what "Red Green Refactor" is. Basically it is the motto of TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red - making your test fail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green - writing a piece of code to make your test pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refactor - cleaning up you mess aka&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/red-green-refactor/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">5b5a2f2b-6b6d-4492-9b43-7e668c42b7f0</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 09:00:15 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today we've been given a task of researching what "Red Green Refactor" is. Basically it is the motto of TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 3 simple steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red - making your test fail&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green - writing a piece of code to make your test pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refactor - cleaning up you mess aka DRY (making your code look nicer AND work)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple enough process but quite powerful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks Archie for making it nice and simple! You are the best!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 2</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Standups (our morning and afternoon meetings) are when you are actually standing up! It makes meetings shorter. And surprisingly more efficient. If only all meetings in business were like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming violently ruins stereotypes about programmers, siting along at home and coding. Programmers communicate more than anyone from the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-2/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b3be5463-0807-4a23-9bcd-8c9ecaa2d5f0</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 22:57:18 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Standups (our morning and afternoon meetings) are when you are actually standing up! It makes meetings shorter. And surprisingly more efficient. If only all meetings in business were like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pair programming violently ruins stereotypes about programmers, siting along at home and coding. Programmers communicate more than anyone from the outside world could ever imagine! And it seems like a very good idea. I had a wonderful pair programming partner today, very positive and committed. It helps a lot to have someone to discuss stuff and it is generally more fun. We did a good part of legendary Boris Bike exercise today. Should finish it by the end of the week.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RSpec is ... well … unusual.  First you write a test, make it fail (I never thought failures could be so exiting!) and only then write code and test it.  But it is super important. &lt;br&gt;
In consulting, people say that you can find 70% of an answer in a question,  but here you can find 70% of your code in tests and errors. Tests seem to be something like a skeleton of the code, that does not let the code fall apart. If you change something in one part of the code, tests immediately inform you if this change ruined something in another part of the code. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation. The second best thing after sleeping! Love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am still fighting for my social life, I went to Ronnie Scott to see Monty Alexander trio today. They were amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more about social life –  my partner tried to buy tickets to Dismaland today. Could someone write a good code for Banksy to manage a queue on the day when tickets go on sale?! It is such an awful mess! Grrrrr...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 1 - Induction</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first day in a month with NO CODING! Surprise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway the day was very intense and productive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day I had plenty of opportunities to chat with people from our cohort and the conclusion is... Our cohort is awesome! I have not seen so many&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-1-induction/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">1948fbab-deef-48ea-b96a-4b63305dc2ad</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2015 21:30:14 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first day in a month with NO CODING! Surprise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway the day was very intense and productive. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day I had plenty of opportunities to chat with people from our cohort and the conclusion is... Our cohort is awesome! I have not seen so many positive open smart beautiful and different people in one room for a long time.  Harry from Cornwall, Philip from Gloucestershire, Michael from North York, Lucy from Melbourne, Matt from Cheshire and all 30+ of us from all over the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And thinking about the induction itself, well, the main words are: very professional, clever and thoughtful. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New words learned: CJO (I wish every company had this position!), educational psychology (!), slackoverflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had some Northern Line madness in the end, got home in 2.5 hours. I do not think I will ever leave Makers before 8 pm again!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Pre-course</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So, I joined the Makers Academy September cohort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start on September 1st, but before that we have to finish the Pre-course. We are well equipped with several tools to go through the pre-course: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MA lessons, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack (where we can help each other) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Google (where strangers can help us)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/pre-course/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">12ef853f-5e4e-4efb-aa8b-43ecaffa7460</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2015 15:14:09 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So, I joined the Makers Academy September cohort. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start on September 1st, but before that we have to finish the Pre-course. We are well equipped with several tools to go through the pre-course: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MA lessons, &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Slack (where we can help each other) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and Google (where strangers can help us)!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id="week1commandline"&gt;Week 1: Command line&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command line interface (CLI) allows you to communicate directly with your computer, with underlying code of your computer, to be precise. You do not need support of graphical user interface (GUI) to create new files and folders, move between the folders and see what's inside, change access to files, to find stuff, etc. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing GUI to CLI feels a bit like removing training wheels form a bicycle. At first it is uncomfortable but later you appreciate the freedom you get. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maker's lesson on CL is very informative and clear, very easy to read and understand even for a newbie (like myself!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New words learned: &lt;code&gt;pwd, ls, cd, mkdir, rmdir, rm, touch, cp, mv&lt;/code&gt; (renaming a file is actually moving a file!), &lt;code&gt;cat, less, chmod, man, find, grep, sudo, shebang&lt;/code&gt; and many many others. Also learned how to use | &amp;lt; &gt; &amp;lt;&amp;lt; to redirect streams. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with all these knowledge and trembling hands I successfully finished the first pre-course challenge. Only 3 weeks later I can say that it was just a kid's stuff...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="week2gitandgithub"&gt;Week 2: Git and Github&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week 2 started on Friday! I had a trip planned for the whole week 2, so had to finish my learnings for the week before it even has started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning git is like receiving an access to a new universe. Because Github is a new universe! Populated with developers only. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Git is a version control system. And you cannot overrate the importance of using it. It helps you to save you work on different stages, to work on different versions of a program, to work on a project with a team, etc. You have to develop a habit to use it but it pays off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing is GitHub! It is like a huge open library of source code. You can keep your code there, but you can also browse through other developers code, fork it, clone it, even improve it (well, I am soooooo far from that now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a developer you are your Github profile. Feeling exposed! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="weeks3ruby"&gt;Weeks 3: Ruby&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the beginning I thought that making mistakes and asking for help could be the most difficult things for me on this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Makers are so good in helping you to ask for help! &lt;br&gt;
There is Slack, where you can communicate with your cohort and seniors, there are Github issues, where you can ask questions, and on week 3 of pre-course you get a mentor! No way you are left on your own!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start learning actual programming language you need help more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruby is a very popular programming language and a very elegant one! The more you learn it the more you appreciate how smart it is. My vocabulary expanded dramatically with words like &lt;code&gt;object, class, method, variable, string, array, hash&lt;/code&gt; and tonns and tonns of method names...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I finished Chris Pine book, finished sections 1 and 2 of Ruby Kickstart, and (the most exciting) started to play on codewars!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codewars are addictive. I have an awful mess at home, barely walk with my dog, and my partner is getting used to this absent look, when I pretend to participate in a conversation but actually can not stop thinking about an unresolved kata... you know...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I forced myself to stick to 7 and 8 kyu kata, to learn how to write more elegant 'ruby style' code. Solving a problem is one thing but solving it with a nice code is so much more satisfying! My favourite trick now is to write &lt;code&gt;if...else..end&lt;/code&gt; sentence in one line with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;condition&amp;gt; ? &amp;lt;if true&amp;gt; : &amp;lt;if false&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. It makes a code look much lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this week's challenge to reach 70 points on codewars was more fun then challenge! &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/"&gt;Stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; helps a lot, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this week I also had my first session of pair programming with my tutor. Loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh! And I also learned to use some Markdown to make my page look nicer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id="week4moreruby"&gt;Week 4: More Ruby&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week I was in Edinburgh for Fringe festival! Watched tonnes of great shows! And I must say that technology is everywhere, even in the &lt;a href="https://english.komische-oper-berlin.de/schedule/magic-flute/"&gt;opera&lt;/a&gt;! And of course in &lt;a href="http://lacaserne.net/index2.php/theatre/eight_eight_seven/"&gt;theatre&lt;/a&gt;! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My learning this week was between the shows, but 4 hour train to Edinburgh and back helped a lot. I covered most part of the Well-Grounded Rubyist by David A. Black. The book is so good! A real page-turner. It is also very smart for the publisher to give you a free ebook (password protected) when you buy a hardcopy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also I did some more katas and started reading about rspec.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I spent my last day before the course writing this post! The fun begins in 15 hours!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Hello, world</title><description>&lt;p&gt;I can't believe it is happening :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p.s. Thanks Usman for &lt;a href="http://usmanj.github.io/setting-up-a-ghost-blog-on-github/"&gt;this post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/hello-world/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">697e047f-6461-4673-9379-209dfba95189</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Aug 2015 15:18:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I can't believe it is happening :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p.s. Thanks Usman for &lt;a href="http://usmanj.github.io/setting-up-a-ghost-blog-on-github/"&gt;this post.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>