<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Learn to code</title><description>Based on a true story</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.6</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2015 21:42:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Days 47-48 Reinventing instagram</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Another weekend, another challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our simple project starts with more than 30 folders and approximately 60 files. And finishes with twice as many...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the inspiration on Saturday morning we went to Hockney exhibition first and then to Frieze. And then to Georgian restaurant! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today I am proud&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-47-48-reinventing-instagram/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">78d1ca1c-16ad-4079-95f0-bcdc264671f3</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2015 21:28:13 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Another weekend, another challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our simple project starts with more than 30 folders and approximately 60 files. And finishes with twice as many...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the inspiration on Saturday morning we went to Hockney exhibition first and then to Frieze. And then to Georgian restaurant! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And today I am proud to present a couple of photos from my weekend &lt;a href="https://calm-tundra-5324.herokuapp.com/pictures"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not quite instagram, but if you use your imagination you can see some remote resemblance...&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Days 44-46 - More magic</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Here I will write about creating a simple project in Rails, about MVC structure, REST, CRUD, routs, Rails command line, Active Record Associations, migrations and schema, and other important things to remember, as soon as I have at least couple of hours...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to bed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-44-46-more-magic/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7f1b2bc4-bafb-4d9c-a792-a8f18a366b9a</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2015 14:21:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Here I will write about creating a simple project in Rails, about MVC structure, REST, CRUD, routs, Rails command line, Active Record Associations, migrations and schema, and other important things to remember, as soon as I have at least couple of hours...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to bed.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 43 - Ada Lovelace Day</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Today is Ada Lovelace day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every girl in tech knows that she was the first computer programmer in the world! It might be true. At least it is nice to believe it. &lt;a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/53131/ada-lovelace-first-computer-programmer"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a good article about her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other great women in tech like &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/10/margaret-hamilton-nasa-apollo/"&gt;Margaret Hamilton&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-43-ada-lovelace-day/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ca41274e-1e0b-431a-9fdc-9be397d7bab7</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 14:21:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Today is Ada Lovelace day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every girl in tech knows that she was the first computer programmer in the world! It might be true. At least it is nice to believe it. &lt;a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/53131/ada-lovelace-first-computer-programmer"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a good article about her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other great women in tech like &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/2015/10/margaret-hamilton-nasa-apollo/"&gt;Margaret Hamilton&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.sandimetz.com/"&gt;Sandi Metz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there are also men. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I do not see any reasons to believe that gender somehow influences the abilities to code. It is equal pain and fun for both.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 42</title><description>&lt;p&gt;In the morning we met our juniors for the first time! &lt;br&gt;
Only 6 weeks ago we were on their place. 6 weeks! Like the whole life! And a good one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have new coaches, they are very cool, but I will miss our old ones, they were geniuses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-42/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ddfa6bfd-9231-4dd9-b07a-538cf5253770</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2015 21:23:41 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the morning we met our juniors for the first time! &lt;br&gt;
Only 6 weeks ago we were on their place. 6 weeks! Like the whole life! And a good one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have new coaches, they are very cool, but I will miss our old ones, they were geniuses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we are going learn Ruby on rails. It is not that we really can learn it in a week, but as always we will give it a try and do our best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://rewalls.com/pic/201111/1024x600/reWalls.com-52370.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the only thing I can say about it is MAGIC! It knows everything. Do not try to do anything your way, Ruby on rails knows better! I think it is the centrepiece of our course. So, the week should be very interesting (as if we've ever had a not interesting one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the evening I went to Dee Dee Bridgewater concert! She was fantastic!  I must admit that the course intensity is tough but bearable, it is my social life intensity that is killing me.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Days 38-41: Strike!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;The end of the week and weekend I spent working mostly on our bowling challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed ok in the beginning, code looked nice, then became heavier, then unreadable and then... I followed one of our coaches advice: "It is always fun to throw everything away and  start from the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-38-41-strike/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">7baedf77-bd69-4974-8c75-7b0c92fd5f69</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2015 16:55:49 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The end of the week and weekend I spent working mostly on our bowling challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed ok in the beginning, code looked nice, then became heavier, then unreadable and then... I followed one of our coaches advice: "It is always fun to throw everything away and  start from the beginning". &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another idea on how to build it. The task became ok again, I wrote a nice engine, it all worked so nicely, that I decided to make an interface. That was not wise. I stopped sleeping at nights. I even came back to the first version of the code, but it made things even worse. I went to a long long walk to a park. And the next day again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then suddenly I had a solution. And it worked! And it involved only reasonable amount of code! And I even had some time to write this post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the lesson was learned - if you need an interface, think about it from the beginning. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://encrypted-tbn1.gstatic.com/images?q=tbn:ANd9GcTvj8_Vboktwy3ik-ItlIzDSxXNU5Rb3P_59yRtGo6HTOY5OLG7" alt="bowling mess"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Days 35-37 Mainly MEAN</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, obviously I do not follow my plan...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least I do not post here every day, but that is because I learn so many things simultaneously! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New knowledge for the last 3 days in few words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MEAN stays for Mongo, Express, Angular and Node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node helps you to run&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-35-37/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">843845c3-7da3-4def-b5aa-17483656b025</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 19:19:21 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Well, obviously I do not follow my plan...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least I do not post here every day, but that is because I learn so many things simultaneously! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New knowledge for the last 3 days in few words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MEAN stays for Mongo, Express, Angular and Node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Node helps you to run your JS program using terminal, just print &lt;code&gt;node &amp;lt;filename.js&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in command line. If you type &lt;code&gt;node&lt;/code&gt; in terminal you can play with JS the same way as you play with Ruby using &lt;code&gt;irb&lt;/code&gt; (but I already got used to console and console.log()). It is not a server, but you can create one with it. And everything is in JS! So no need to switch from JS to Ruby (or another language) and back. An important thing about Node is that it is asynchronous, which makes it very effective. But you have to use callbacks for that, and it is not so straight forward in the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Express is something like Sinatra, but for Node JS. It seems easier and more intuitive, but may be it is because we already learned how to deal with Sinatra. For express template engine is not needed, it can handle html files directly, it is good for simple projects but for more complicated you can use Jade or ejs (they are like erb for ruby).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongo is a non SQL database, it stores information as JSON, and it seems a bit chaotic, but may be it is not, I just started to play with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Angular... I am not sure yet. We will have the whole week dedicated to it, so I will write about it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.udemy.com/node-js-tutorial/#0"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is fantastic blog post on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 34</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Finally have time to think about lab week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lab week is a week when we are on our own. No fixed plan. Everyone does what he needs most: review of previous challenges, learn JS, explore new technologies or sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to finish JS by Jon Duckett (at least&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-34/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">37845033-743b-458e-b424-b5ffd291c9cb</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Oct 2015 09:39:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Finally have time to think about lab week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lab week is a week when we are on our own. No fixed plan. Everyone does what he needs most: review of previous challenges, learn JS, explore new technologies or sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to finish JS by Jon Duckett (at least 50-60 pages per day),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to learn more about MEAN (todo project from scotch.io? rps in JS? smth else?),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to pair program at least 3 days of the week,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to attend standups with my byte every day,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to post about my progress every day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too ambitious? May be. We'll see.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 33</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Rugby day! &lt;br&gt;
Beer, pizza and friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole day without coding! Already miss it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-33/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6f5f4eba-2380-43b0-8b18-5f14f14ad37d</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2015 22:38:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Rugby day! &lt;br&gt;
Beer, pizza and friends!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole day without coding! Already miss it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 32</title><description>&lt;p&gt;It was seniors graduation day today. &lt;br&gt;
Their final projects were amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the middle of the course (equator as they say in uni) for us, we are officially seniors now. Time to think what our final projects could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week is a lab week. So hope to have&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-32/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">62000e20-06c6-43ef-a2a0-b3bc32c40cc4</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 21:34:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It was seniors graduation day today. &lt;br&gt;
Their final projects were amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the middle of the course (equator as they say in uni) for us, we are officially seniors now. Time to think what our final projects could be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week is a lab week. So hope to have plenty of time to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Days 29-31</title><description>&lt;p&gt;By activity in a blog you can always see when friends are in town!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will try to write more about new things learnt this week (JSON, ajax, jquery, APIs) later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for now more concerts, cocktails and fun!!!&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-29-31/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">dc73c1e1-d068-425b-ab7e-42615dc3cb60</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;By activity in a blog you can always see when friends are in town!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will try to write more about new things learnt this week (JSON, ajax, jquery, APIs) later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for now more concerts, cocktails and fun!!!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 28: JavaScript!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Can we learn a new language in a week? I'll tell you on Friday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can feel already that comparing to Ruby JS is pain. Syntax is crazy, and errors... well, it does not know much about what went wrong... and I do not know either! was it a&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-28/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">56df40b1-0903-4f0d-adcc-9bfdab448218</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 21:43:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Can we learn a new language in a week? I'll tell you on Friday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I can feel already that comparing to Ruby JS is pain. Syntax is crazy, and errors... well, it does not know much about what went wrong... and I do not know either! was it a test, a code or just a stupid typo! 'Expect undefined to be true'...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;console.log() is my best friend for the next 4 days!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Days 26-27. Proper weekend!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;This week we built a clone of Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, very simple version of it, but still...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was the most difficult weekend challenge so far. I started on Saturday at 9 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 2 pm I had to have a break as I had tickets to Dismaland and&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/days-26-27-proper-weekend/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">c3515be9-3498-4bec-b3db-bb6e0608cf13</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2015 13:37:51 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;This week we built a clone of Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, very simple version of it, but still...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was the most difficult weekend challenge so far. I started on Saturday at 9 am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 2 pm I had to have a break as I had tickets to Dismaland and needed to catch 3pm train from Paddington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued in a train. And a couple of times I was so stuck that I was literally ready to cry. When you have an error and you have no clue how to deal with it! And so many files and folders so you cannot figure out which one could be failing...  And no internet connection... And you do not know where you are and at what station you need to change the train!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I finished it on my way back! And I have the whole Sunday for myself! For the first time since the course has started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was not so bad after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/IluepGs.jpg" alt="Imgur"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 25</title><description>&lt;p&gt;By Friday I  realised that everything I wrote on Tuesday about project structure and connecting files was just a kids stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our project has two times more folders, and files, and gems, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am amazed by the speed we learn things.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-25/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">6ad4aa8b-15de-4b13-af5e-0c56cea81ef4</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 11:43:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;By Friday I  realised that everything I wrote on Tuesday about project structure and connecting files was just a kids stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our project has two times more folders, and files, and gems, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am amazed by the speed we learn things.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 23-24: Bugs days</title><description>&lt;p&gt;It all started with Apple iPhone Software Update (to version 9.0). iPhone just stuck and did not want to move anywhere from the page 'slide to upgrade'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs that we make and catch during our learning process are not so epic of course, but sometimes an extra letter, a&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-23-24-bug-days/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">ef32a28d-f47e-4ec8-8f6e-8b5f842aa8f8</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 14:49:08 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It all started with Apple iPhone Software Update (to version 9.0). iPhone just stuck and did not want to move anywhere from the page 'slide to upgrade'.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs that we make and catch during our learning process are not so epic of course, but sometimes an extra letter, a typo, lack of a dot or comma can easily ruin several hours of your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I got a flue bug, had to stay at home and decided to write this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how to find a bug?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, as a beginner, the easiest way to catch a bug is to print out everything that's going on in my code. I put a print (&lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;puts&lt;/code&gt;) statement before and after every line of my code, with a short explanation of what I am printing. Then I literally can read when and where a bug appears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are better ways. For example, using &lt;code&gt;pry&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;byebug&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pry is very similar to irb, but has some extra features. &lt;br&gt;
To use pry, first you need to install it using &lt;code&gt;gem install pry&lt;/code&gt; or include &lt;code&gt;gem 'pry'&lt;/code&gt; to your &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; and run &lt;code&gt;bundle install&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you need to &lt;code&gt;require pry&lt;/code&gt; in a file, where you want to find a bug, and print &lt;code&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; before the place where you think the bug can be. When you run your program, it will stop at &lt;code&gt;binding.pry&lt;/code&gt; point. And then you can print next lines in pry, receiving feedback on what is going on after each line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using byebug is similar. You install it using &lt;code&gt;gem install byebug&lt;/code&gt; or include it into your &lt;code&gt;Gemfile&lt;/code&gt; and run &lt;code&gt;bundle install&lt;/code&gt;. Then you &lt;code&gt;require byebug&lt;/code&gt; in a file anf print &lt;code&gt;byebug&lt;/code&gt; in your file where you want your program to stop running. And then you can play with byebug, the same way as you play with irb or pry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bugs have no chances!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://etm.freshegg.com/customModules/apuldramRoses/products/images/PROVADO%20ULTIMATE%20BUG%20KILLER%20CONCENTRATE.jpg" alt=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>Day 22: It gets serious!</title><description>&lt;p&gt;2 main things I learned today are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to structure your program,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to deploy it to heroku.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most difficult thing in structure is to create all necessary files and to connect them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is how a structure of our simple project looks like now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;project  
|___.git(folder, lots&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/day-22/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">8203f8cd-0a1f-4ae1-955d-771c1f0fe808</guid><dc:creator>Yana Proskurina</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 20:53:24 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;2 main things I learned today are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to structure your program,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how to deploy it to heroku.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most difficult thing in structure is to create all necessary files and to connect them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is how a structure of our simple project looks like now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;project  
|___.git(folder, lots of things going on here)
|___Gemfile
|___Gemfile.lock
|___app
|   |__app.rb
|   |__data_mapper_setup.rb
|   |
|   |__models
|   |  |__first_model.rb
|   |  |__second_model.rb
|   |
|   |__views
|      |__index.erb
|      |__first_page
|         |__new.erb
|         |__old.erb
|
|___config.ru
|
|___.rspec
|___spec
    |___features
    |   |__first_feature_test_spec.spec
    |   |__second_feature_test_spec.spec
    |   |__third_feature_test_spec.spec
    |
    |___spec_helper.spec
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only three weeks of learning and I understand what each file is needed for! Well, I think I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;App folder is all about our app, spec folder is about tests (same as .rspec file), .git is a folder with version control files, Gemfiles are about gems and config is to start our program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connecting all these files is a separate story. We use &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;require_relative&lt;/code&gt; to connect files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;app.rb (our controller file for now) requires data_mapper_setup.rb, data_mapper_setup.rb requires model files (and that's how app.rb also knows about model files);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in .rspec we require spec_helper and spec_helper.rb  in its turn requires app.rb and also data_mapper_setup.rb (only now while writing this post I realised I can do that instead of requiring data_mapper_setup from each test!);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in addition we require sinatra in app.rb, data mapper in data_mapper_setup, capybara and database cleaner in spec_helper.spec.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All clear and very logical, right? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition we had a very nice adventure to deploy our little bookmark manager program to heroku!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heroku is super cool and simple, but when you use it for the first time and your program needs a database... it might be not so straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here we had to learn the importance of environment in Sinatra. By pure coincidence I read "Jump start Sinatra" in a tube in the morning, and there was a little chapter called 'Environments'. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, "... there are three predefined environments: development, production(when your app is live on the server), and test... To check what environment the app is running in, the helper methods &lt;code&gt;production?&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;development?&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;test?&lt;/code&gt; will return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;..."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used this couple of times in Gemfile, like this:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;group :test do  
  gem 'rspec'
  gem 'capybara'
end  
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I never paid attention. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it actually means, is that depending on environment particular gems will or will not be used. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when you use database it means, that depending on environment, path to a database will be different (when on local, database will be on your computer, when online using heroku database should be on ... heroku! Obvious, right?). So, we need to tell heroku to create database first, and in data_mapper_setup.rb we needed to indicate a path to a database depending on environment in which our program is running!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for test environment we used database postgres://localhost/bookmark_manager_test&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;for development environment we used database postgres://localhost/bookmark_manager_development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and for production environment in heroku it is &lt;code&gt;ENV['DATABASE_URL']&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To copy your database to heroku you do &lt;code&gt;heroku run console&lt;/code&gt; and...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I am not sure, will check it tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href="https://serene-scrubland-3780.herokuapp.com/"&gt;this is&lt;/a&gt; what we have so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much, but I am soooooooo proud!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>